# Yinan (Tom) Xuan

yxuan@ucsd.edu
https://www.yinanxuan.com

My research interests lie at the intersection of ubiquitous computing, health monitoring, and implicit interaction. I am interested in using passive sensing to understand human activities and physiological status by utilizing my expertise in applied machine learning and prototyping skills in both software and hardware.

### Education

### University of California, San Diego

La Jolla, CA

Ph.D. in Electrical & Computer Engineering

July 2020 – Dec. 2024 (expected)

Advisor: Edward Wang

Areas: Ubiquitous Health Sensing

Sept. 2017 – June 2020

M.S. in Biological Science Advisor: Jing Wang

Thesis: Computer Vision Aided Drosophila Gut Imaging Data Collection and Analysis

B.S. in Physiology & Neuroscience Sept.

Minor: Cognitive Science Honors: MAGNA CUM LAUDE (GPA 3.89/4.00)

## Experience

#### **Graduate Student Researcher**

Oct. 2019 – Present

Sept. 2013 - June 2017

La Jolla, CA

University of California, San Diego Electrical and Computer Engineering Department, Jacobs School of Engineering

DigiHealth Lab

- Developed a calibration method that enable accurate and consistent camera photoplethysmography measurement across multiple Android smart phones
- Designed and built BPClip, an ultra low-cost blood pressure monitoring smartphone attachment consisted of 3D-printed hardware accessories and on-device ML/OpenCV Android application.
- Designed and implemented SpecTracle, a vision-based unobtrusive facial tracking system for AR, which consists of fisheye lens cameras controlled by Raspberry Pi and an image based neural network model.
- Implemented a Unity exercising game prototype that uses IMU signals on Vuzix AR glasses
- Built an embedded system that allows compression testing for various materials and designs.

### **Indie Game Developer**

June 2021 – Present

- Project Management: Coordinated among team members and made decisions about development details and timeline.
- Development: Built all elements in the game with C# in Unity 2D, including but not limited to: Items, Quests, Dialogues, and Cut Scenes.
- Gameplay Design: Designed player experience and overall gameplay system.
- · Technical Art: Designed and built VFXs with 2D lighting, shader graphs and particle system.

#### **Graduate Student Researcher**

April 2018 – June 2020

University of California, San Diego

La Jolla, CA

Section of Neurobiology, Division of Biological Science

Wang Lab

- Designed and implemented an olfaction VR device as a novel instrument to observe odor guided behaviors in Drosophila
- Designed, implemented and deployed an image processing software to facilitate bio-imaging data analysis pipeline that profiles *Drosophila* intestinal cells' response to different nutrients.
- Designed, implemented and deployed an automated solenoid valve control system for perfusion experiments that can independently control up to 22 valves.
- Collaborated in building and testing a customized three-photon fluorescent imaging microscope.

• Built a feedback controlled temperature-based anesthetic platform to facilitate surgery process on *Drosophila*.

### **Undergraduate Student Researcher**

University of California, San Diego

Division of Otolaryngology–Head and Neck Surgery, Department of Surgery

Ongkeko Lab Advisor: Weg Ongkeko

· Studied the role of long non-coding RNAs in head and neck squamous cell cancer.

- Designed and conducted in vitro experiments for various projects.

### **Research Internship**

June 2016 – Aug. 2016

Jan 2014 – June 2017

Camarillo, CA

La Jolla, CA

AskGene Pharmaceutical Inc.

• Collaborated in cell line development selecting clone cells with the highest titer.

· Purified recombinant antibodies using Protein-A Affinity Chromatography.

### Skills

#### **Software**

Languages: Python, Kotlin, C#, C++, MATLAB, Java, JavaScript, SQL (MySQL)

Machine Learning Models: Neural Networks, SVM, Hierarchical Clustering, DBSCAN, Gaussian Mixture Model, etc.

Data Analysis/Preprocessing: Dimension Reduction, Signal Processing, Computer Vision / Image Processing, etc.

Mobile Development: iOS (Swift), Android (Kotlin/JAVA), Bluetooth Low Energy

Embedded System Programming: Zephyr w/ nRF51 & nRF52 series, Arduino, Bluetooth Low Energy

Web Development: HTML/CSS, Bootstrap, React, Node.js

#### Hardware

Rapid Prototyping: SolidWorks, 3D printing with SLA/FDM using rigid/flexible material, laser cutting

Embedded System Prototyping: PCB design, hardware/component selection, Raspberry Pi

Free-space Optics

Compressed Gas Cylinder Handling

#### **Biotech**

Animal Handling: Mice, Drosophila, C. elegans

Benchwork: cell culture, RNA extraction, qRT-PCR, transfection, etc.

#### **Publications**

### Papers under Review

- 1. **Xuan, Y.**, Barry, C., Antipa, N., Wang, E. A Calibration Method for Smartphone Camera Photophlethysmography
- 2. **Xuan, Y.**, Viswanath, V., Chu, S., Bartolf, O., Echterhoff, J., Wang, E. *SpecTracle: Wearable Facial Motion Tracking from Unobstructing Peripheral Cameras*

#### Peer-Reviewed Publications

- 3. **Xuan, Y.,** Barry, C., De Souza, J. et al. *Ultra-low-cost mechanical smartphone attachment for no-calibration blood pressure measurement*. **Nature Scientific Reports** 13, 8105 (2023). https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-023-34431-1
- 4. Barry, C., Souza, J., **Xuan, Y.**, Holden, J., Granholm, E., Wang, E. *Enabling Smartphone Pupillometry using a Facial Identification Camera in At-Home Environments*. **CHI 2022 Best Paper Honorable Mention Award** https://dl.acm.org/doi/10.1145/3491102.3502493
- 5. Lin, H.-H., Kuang, M. C., Hossain, I., **Xuan**, **Y.**, Beebe, L., Shepherd, A. K., Rolandi, M., Wang, J. W. (2022). A nutrient-specific gut hormone arbitrates between courtship and feeding. In **Nature**. Springer Science and Business Media LLC. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-022-04408-7

- 6. Yu, V., Rahimy, M., Korrapati, A., **Xuan, Y.**, Zou, A. E., Krishnan, A. R., Tsui, T., Aguilera, J. A., Advani, S., Crotty Alexander, L. E., Brumund, K. T., Wang-Rodriguez, J., amp; Ongkeko, W. M. (2016). *Electronic cigarettes induce DNA strand breaks and cell death independently of nicotine in cell lines*. Oral Oncology, 52, 58–65. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.oraloncology.2015.10.018
- 7. Zou, A. E., Ku, J., Honda, T. K., Yu, V., Kuo, S. Z., Zheng, H., **Xuan, Y.**, Saad, M. A., Hinton, A., Brumund, K. T., Lin, J. H., Wang-Rodriguez, J., amp; Ongkeko, W. M. (2015). *Transcriptome sequencing uncovers novel long noncoding and small nucleolar RNAs dysregulated in head and neck squamous cell carcinoma*. RNA, 21(6), 1122–1134. https://doi.org/10.1261/rna.049262.114
- 8. Zou, A. E., Zheng, H., Saad, M. A., Rahimy, M., Ku, J., Kuo, S. Z., Honda, T. K., Wang-Rodriguez, J., **Xuan, Y.**, Korrapati, A., Yu, V., Singh, P., Grandis, J. R., King, C. C., Lippman, S. M., Wang, X. Q., Hinton, A., amp; Ongkeko, W. M. (2016). *The non-coding landscape of head and neck squamous cell carcinoma*. Oncotarget, 7(32), 51211–51222. https://doi.org/10.18632/oncotarget.9979

#### Posters

- 9. Zou, A. E., Krishnan, A. R., **Xuan**, **Y.**, Saad, M. A., Korrapati, A., Advani, S. J., Wang-Rodriguez, J., amp; Ongkeko, W. (2016). Abstract 977: *RNA-sequencing analysis implicates novel non-coding RNAs in human papillomavirus-associated head and neck squamous cell carcinoma*. Molecular and Cellular Biology, Genetics. https://doi.org/10.1158/1538-7445.am2016-977
- 10. Korrapati, A., Yu, V., Saad, M. A., Rahimy, M., **Xuan**, **Y.**, Zou, A., Krishnan, A., Brumund, K., amp; Ongkeko, W. M. (2016). Abstract 4069: *The carcinogenic effects of electronic cigarettes in oral cancer*. Tumor Biology. https://doi.org/10.1158/1538-7445.am2016-4069
- 11. Ku, J., Zou, A. E., Honda, T. K., Zheng, H., Saad, M. A., Yu, V., **Xuan, Y.**, Singh, P., Rahimy, M., Kuo, S. Z., Ongkeko, W. M., amp; Wang-Rodriguez, J. (2015). Abstract 3836: *Identification of key survival-correlating microRNAs and Piwi-interacting RNAs dysregulated in head and neck squamous cell carcinoma*. Molecular and Cellular Biology. https://doi.org/10.1158/1538-7445.am2015-3836
- 12. Honda, T. K., Zou, A., Yu, V., Zheng, H., Kuo, S., Saad, M., **Xuan, Y.**, Singh, P., Wang-Rodriguez, J., amp; Ongkeko, W. M. (2015). Abstract 151: *Transcriptome-wide expression profiling of long noncoding and small nucleolar RNAs in head and neck squamous cell carcinomas identifies novel transcripts associated with survival*. Molecular and Cellular Biology. https://doi.org/10.1158/1538-7445.am2015-151

# Teaching and Mentoring Experience

#### **Teaching Assistant**

2023 Spring - UCSD ECE 16 Rapid Hardware and Software Design for Interfacing with the World

2022 Winter - UCSD ECE 16

2018 Fall - UCSD BIPN 100 Human Physiology I

#### Mentorship

2022 - Grace Jin, undergraduate researcher from UCSD CSE department

2022 - Joseph Kuo, undergraduate researcher from UCSD ESE department

2021 - MAE student team, undergraduate capstone project

2020 - Sunny Chu, undergraduate researcher from UCSD ECE department

2020 - Owen Bartolf, undergraduate researcher from UCSD CSE department

### Service

- Reviewer for The Lancet Digital Health
- Reviewer for Frontiers In Digital Health
- Reviewer for IEEE VR 2023
- Reviewer for CHI 2023 Papers
- Reviewer for ISWC 2022 Notes Briefs
- Reviewer for UbiComp/ISWC 2020 Posters and Demos

# Membership & Honors

- Member of Phi Beta Kappa Honor Society
- Member of Muir College's Senior Honors Caledonian Society

### Languages

- Mandarin Native Speaker
- English Professional
- Japanese Limited Professional (JLPT N1 Equivalent)
- Cantonese Daily Communication